knowledge is power
[Music]
welcome to the junkyard love podcast
ladies and gentlemen i'm here with zach
beach welcome zach
thanks jacob thanks so much for having
me yeah happy to have you on man you uh
you messaged me um you reached out to me
on instagram and i was like actually
yeah let's let's squeeze you in i know i
had mentioned uh i have my backlog of
pod match people but uh
i immediately was like cool this is
gonna be a great conversation right up
my alley um it seems like you are
interested in a lot of the things that
i'm interested in
you excel in all these different areas
so let's kind of give people who have
never heard of yet they don't know
anything about you what what do you do
what do i do
um
i just want to thank you again for
having me and i appreciate your
listeners uh listening to me because i
am committed to one thing and that is
love
and i want everyone at the end of the
show to know that they deserve all the
love that their heart can have and
handle and that you are loved and you
belong and you're beautiful and perfect
just the way that you are and there's
nothing you need to do change or improve
about yourself
uh to be worthy of love and even at the
end of the day when we make mistakes
where things don't go the way that we
want
you are still worthy of belonging worthy
of love and belonging
so many years ago i decided to devote
myself to love and i do think of my work
in the world as being on the level of
the body the heart and the mind
so on the level of the body my work
involves yoga getting people in touch
with their own bodies partnering yoga
and thai massage getting bodies to
connect with other bodies
on the level of the heart i love poetry
the language of the heart and the
language of love
and on the level of the mind i lecture
write and workshops and do coaching as
well love coaching helping people
strengthen their own
loving relationships
and that to means the power of intention
is it's open-ended and there's a million
ways to
live from whatever intention you set for
your own life whether it's peace or
compassion or love
and it's taken me to really wonderful
places in the world and i also encourage
listeners to live from their own
intention to think about what really
matters to them most in life to think
about why they are here on this planet
and to make sure they're living in line
with those inner values
well so obviously this is a very uh
natural spot for you to fill um it seems
like it goes hand in hand with your
personality and what you're all about
how did you how did you find this
intention you know for someone who's not
really thought consciously
what what do you mean intention you know
you just pick something and you aim at
it and that's what you do like how did
you stumble upon this for yourself
um that would be lovely if it was easy
right um i do kind of think of my path
as that quote that you might know that a
fool a fool who persists in his folly
eventually becomes wise
and mom i'm still not even to the wise
part yeah i'm kind of halfway in between
um
but i would say my path originally
did not begin with love it began with a
search for truth
right a search for is there any kind of
underlying reality to that which we
perceive
and really thinking about
why are we here why are humans here what
does it mean to be a good person those
really fundamental questions that we all
ask ourselves
and it's crazy to me because no matter
where i went in the world rather it was
a
lecture hall at some university or a
church or a temple or a synagogue i
heard the same message again and again
wherever i went on this search for truth
that no matter the question
the answer is love
and when i do talk about love some
people are like oh my god this hippie
like just tells me to love everyone
and i'd like to remind everyone that
this is grounded in science neuroscience
social psychology the idea that we all
need love did not originate with the
beatles it originated with an
understanding of how human beings
develop
we come into this world extraordinarily
dependent on others to take care of
ourselves to give us the food shelter
and care that we need to survive
and that need for connection belonging
continues for the rest of our life
right and i love all the research that's
coming out about how important social
connection is
for our own mental health and well-being
and
some of the research for example says
that poor social connection
is just as bad as smoking a pack of
cigarettes a day or being overly obese
in terms of health and longevity
so it didn't originate with some pie in
the sky hippie ideal but it's really
grounded in how we as human beings are
built how our mind is wired to connect
with others
and
when you were like oh what does it mean
to live with intention
do you just choose it and then you're
done with it that would again be lovely
but it's iterative
right so living with intention is a
matter of one reflecting like what
really matters most to you in this life
and then trying your best to live from
that intention right so you might wake
up in the morning and you say i'm gonna
love myself today and then you go to the
mirror and you see a big zit on your
forehead and you're like you are so ugly
and you're like dang it
lost already
um but that's why it's a practice right
it is an iterative
uh matter of continually coming back to
our intention whether it's for peace or
love or compassion or understanding or
forgiveness
and along with that practice you're
constantly making adjustments to your
path constantly figuring out what really
works and what doesn't
right
and so sometimes like we think that
we're on the right path we climb one
metaphor is we reach a wall we get to
the top of the ladder we look over the
wall we're like wait a second this was
the wrong wall
and then we have to go an entirely
different path so just the same for me i
thought i was on a path for truth and
then truth led me to love now i'm on a
path of love so who knows what this one
might take me
wow beautiful okay so when you first
began this journey um
i'll just say for me when i kind of
started
turning turning my my intention inwardly
you know kind of asking myself these
similar things that you were saying it
you know um
like like what what does it mean to
what is my intention what is mine what
is my focus like what am i what what
should i be doing you know these sort of
things that kind of make you question
yourself like what am i what's a human
and and why does love feel good and and
whatnot did you have um
oh did you have any sort of like
breaking moment or any sort of like what
you would consider a spiritual awakening
of any sorts um
i don't know if you use these
terminologies but you know some people
talk about stepping onto the path of
enlightenment that sort of thing i don't
know if you um stumbled in that
direction like what what kind of sparked
you to do this sort of thing
well
i do think of my path as almost a
continuous process of awakening
or to put it a different way i do think
of the life path
as a series of exercises in awakening or
spiritual awakening
that our
task as human beings the reason we were
reincarnated in this form that's just
one way of putting it
is simply to awaken
and that everything we experience in
this life is all grist for the mill
it's all signposts and exercises that we
can use to facilitate our own awakening
and i wouldn't say at any point there
was like this sudden moment it has been
this continuous process and this
continuous deepening
and
it's interesting kind of the way you
formulated your question because it's
like oh i've been trying to kind of
figure this out or have you been trying
to figure this out
because something that you discover on
the path is
thinking
will not get you there
is
the mind is limited in its abilities and
its conceptualizations
and to me spirituality is
almost anything that goes beyond the
mind right this is what eckhart tolle
says spirituality is anything that goes
beyond the continuous movement of
thinking
right or mark epstein says that
spirituality is anything that transcends
our personality right anything that goes
beyond this sense of ego this sense of a
limited self caught up in this body and
stuck in an alien universe
right
so
it you can't think yourself there
although the path of mental discipline
and mastery is an important one but it
is a matter of discovering other
dimensions to our being other dimensions
to being human
and one important dimension of course is
the heart is the heart space
which is why i was never a big fan of
the term mindfulness
because when we bring our full body our
full present moment awareness it
there's no mind left so i often refer to
it as either a heartfulness because
you're bringing your full heart
or b
tuning into something we already talked
about i think of mindfulness as being
re-mindfulness
where you continually remind yourself
of your intention of why you are here
but i often also think of mindfulness as
simply loving connected
presence
at the same time
and again this is this practice that we
continue to do
and
in yoga we do have this kind of basic
idea that
nirvana and samsara are the same
or the end and the means are the same
and if you think that you're getting
somewhere or that you're trying to
attain something you've already
made a mistake
basically like if you're meditating to
attain enlightenment like you're not
meditating because you've already
separated yourself from some
future oriented goal
and
we can come to kind of a understanding
that
if we are looking for like an
unconditioned aspect of our experience
then it's not going to be found anywhere
than right here right now right not
anywhere outside of yourself not
anywhere somewhere in the future that
you are trying to go towards
because if you can gain it guess what
you can lose it
and therefore it's just
back to the world of conditions
[Music]
yeah wow yeah it uh it it is interesting
uh i feel like
my perception i've always been pretty
fascinated with time it's always just
been um the concept has always just
caught my attention um my my tattoo
sleeve actually on my left side is a
representation of time is the four
seasons
but it's interesting because i feel like
when i got it when i first got into you
know i never really understood my
obsession with time i knew that i liked
it and i knew that it was fascinating i
knew it was really cool to think about
and talk about with people i have i've
um you know friends who study physics
and it's really cool to talk about time
with them but
uh the farther i kind of
you know again not that we will arrive
but i guess the more i get in tune with
my spiritual self um the more time
my perception of time is different of
like this
not you know sitting in meditation not
thinking i'm going to arrive or like
okay if i do the right things then i'm
going to like it's going to turn on or
whatever but it's more of just sitting
with
of course it is exactly how it is right
now you know you just you just become
acceptance of of how it is right now in
order for it to
kind of
propagate the future that you maybe
believe in um
so okay so
as far as your your world in meditation
and yoga
when it
let's see what question do i want to ask
um
i could touch on a few things that you
just said yeah
go ahead i'll ramble on into nothingness
for a while so thank you
well i love because you were like you
know i often think about time
right
yeah and
that is part of the fundamental inquiry
that we find on the spiritual path which
is the human path which is the same path
that we're all walking just the series
of exercises and awakening
and it does
tap into like
those fundamental questions like why are
we here
what is life why is there something
rather than nothing and
it is a matter of penetrating
whether what we experience is
true
versus just like an artificial reality
created by the mind
right so then we get into okay what is
space what is matter what is existence
what is consciousness and what is time
is of course wrapped into all of that
and part of our
path of viveka wise discrimination is
differentiating between what is part of
our real experience and is there any
underlying truth to that
and the basic idea is that once we are
able to discover that truth then we do
attain a certain level of awakening or
insight so you probably know vapasana
just simply means insight meaning that
if you have insight into the true nature
of reality then you'll
awaken
and you absolutely tap into this idea
that we don't find it out there but we
find it in here
so there's there's this quote by
paramahansa yogananda that i love and he
says that it is not the physicist
but it is the self-realized master to
understand the true nature of
reality we discover as soon as we look
within that we're just a reflection of
the
cosmos that this microcosm is a
reflection of the macrocosm
and
we look within to discover if there is
any underlying truth
and of course as soon as we look in the
mind and observe the mind we realize
just the idea of time is a total
illusion
created by the mind right the only thing
that ever exists is this present
unfolding now it's the mind that creates
a
future that no longer that doesn't exist
and it's creates a past that's already
gone
and then you're like okay well if time
is an illusion created by the mind if my
body sends mind complex is an illusion
created by the mind what is real right
is what is true and that's the path
um
can we expand a little bit on um because
i like explaining this i i've spoken
with people and spoken with friends um
kind of about i've used the word you
know anxiety and depression you know so
often anxiety is you're you're thinking
you're right here right now but you're
thinking towards into the future what
might happen um or you're depressed
often we're looking at the past where
we're upset about something that might
have happened so can you elaborate a
little bit more on what you mean by you
know all we have is right now how is
when we're thinking about the future how
is that not right now
yeah i've i've also heard that idea and
you know if you're i wonder if it was
true or suzuki or one of those roshi
masters but this basic idea that if
you're
anxious you're living in the future if
you're depressed you're living in the
past
and
i don't know how many like therapists in
psychology would agree with such like a
blatant
reductionist statement because there
might be some other factors involved
but it is really important to understand
how the mind works
in order to become free of it in order
for us not to be controlled by the mind
in order for us to realize that what we
might be experiencing might be very real
as we say
but it's not true right
and
one of the things the mind does is it's
dual and it's understanding it splits
the world in its understanding and one
of the things it does is yes create a
future or create a past
and create any sort of abstract concept
that we then get tapped into and caught
up in and thinking that it is some
version of the truth
and there is a matter of turning the
mind into a slave as we say and not a
master and tapping into other ways of
being in this world
right so there's a quote by
i want to say thomas merton the
christian mystic and he says that
our bodies
know that they belong
it's our mind that makes us homeless
which taps into this idea that yeah if
we want to be in your present in this
moment it's really not hard people think
it's like oh some mindfulness some
mental trick you want to be in this
moment
be in your body
your body is breathing beating its heart
pumping its blood feeling sensing in the
right here and the right now and it's
the mind that is going to take you away
from being in this continuous unfolding
moment
another phrase that i've heard i'm not
sure who who said this but
it goes the mind creates the abyss
and it's the heart that crosses it
which again taps into other dimensions
of our being so first we have our body
that is always in this present unfolding
moment and of course we have this heart
um so i sometimes think that like yes
the mind will break the world up into a
million pieces
and it's the heart that will put it back
together
and what i mean by like yeah the mind
will divide up the world it kind of
catches it in what i call a cognitive
net it separates things categorizes
things
you know these are this species this is
this far away this is the this happened
in the past has to happen in the future
in order for us to understand anything
it comes from a level of duality comes
from a level of separation
which is one way of observing and
understanding the universe but there are
of course other ways
so
um
you know there's this metaphor that the
buddha uses he says right now there's an
arrow in your leg and you could spend a
lot of time
conceptualizing thinking about where the
error came from and who shot it and what
the trajectory and the speed of the
arrow was that is now in your leg or you
could attend to the wound and attend to
the suffering
and that's kind of my approach to
certain things that the mind does like
potentially generate a sense of anxiety
of the future depression of the past as
you could think like okay like how is
this working where did it come from was
it my childhood trauma et cetera et
cetera and that can be very helpful
or we can just attend to the fact that
human beings have a penchant for making
themselves miserable
for making them making ourselves suffer
and
the mind is the one constantly imagining
and wanting things to be different than
the way that they are creating a certain
level of suffering
imagining a future that could be better
or a past that was better and now things
are much worse
and
rather than necessarily
figure out
those dynamics we can
simply attend to this reality that there
is some suffering and we can bring our
heart
to bridge the abyss to
and we can come into our bodies to come
back home
yeah it reminds me i was thinking of the
i saw this meme that was like some sort
of spiritual meme that was uh when i
find the person responsible for all of
my suffering and it wasn't looking
you know um can we could we elaborate a
little bit more on um
the difference between like heart and
mind or kind of like dropping into your
heart center you know i've done plenty
of meditations where
it's so subtle you know it's so subtle
but it's so beautifully subtle where um
maybe you first sit down and so your
mind's you know a little bit racy um
kind of going through you're you're
trying to concentrate on your breath in
this meditation for example um and then
i've had the uh the person guiding the
meditation would say you know drop into
your heart center they would give you
different cues or different ways of kind
of like bringing your awareness from
either following your breath or your
thinking mind or just you know one
pointed on something
and dropping it into your heart and um
there's this it is very subtle but if
you can kind of drop your attention into
your heart
it's it's a
it's very difficult to describe but like
you you
do become detached from your thoughts in
a way um if you're able to kind of like
um
you know
there's a
i've for the definite or the uh the
example of kind of ringing a bell and at
the end you're not just trying to like
where's the ringing of the bell you
listen for the end you kind of just sit
in the silence of the echo as after the
bell rings
um and there's something similar to that
when dropping into the heart so does any
of that spark anything for you when i
say kind of dropping into the heart does
that um
does that ring ring any bells for you so
to say
indeed absolutely there's so many
different
ways i could take this i'll just begin
with a few basic ideas because one you
mentioned it's really hard to describe
the heart space it's really hard to
explain
and
that's it right because we're trying to
use the mind
to
explain something that of course
goes beyond the mind
right
as alan watts would say
just as water cannot rise above its own
level
so too
the mind cannot rise above the level of
thinking
right
and this
again to me is the entire spiritual
journey
some say the spiritual journey is a
journey of 18 inches
traveling from here pointing to my head
in case people can't see from here down
to here
from the head to the heart
but but i also come back to a poem by
wendell berry and he says actually the
spiritual journey is one inch it's even
shorter than 18 where we finally arrive
at the ground beneath our feet where we
finally arrive in the here and now
but of course human beings are we're
little chatter boxes we love to talk
about things and we can try our best to
describe it and
you
we're starting to use
kind of a more metaphoric language right
to describe the heart when we say like
oh we have to go deeper into this area
of our being
and this to me is the power of metaphor
the power of poetry to describe a
certain way of being that does
potentially go beyond the mind that does
tap us into
another way of being
because we are
as we say in zen just fingers pointing
to the moon
using words to describe a fundamentally
indescribable experience
and metaphor can be a really wonderful
way to get closer closer to the moon
because it taps more
is another way to describe the capacity
of the heart
because we get so focused on
limited thoughts of the mind we don't
realize the space that is of course
around
that thought or we don't we get so
caught up in
the contents of our awareness rather
than awareness itself
right so there's a famous dialogue of a
monk who
drew a bird on the chalkboard or the
white board and he said what is this a
picture of and people were like oh it's
a bird he said no
it's the sky
with a bird passing through it
and that to me is the level of the heart
is a more expansive
spacious
level of awareness
that is able to
say hold one's thoughts or even emotions
but from a place of acceptance
right so when we get into our true
nature
true nature is not the mind
all right have you ever like introduced
yourself maybe to someone who
you know english isn't their first
language and you say my name
is jacob or i would say my name is zach
no one puts their
hand on their head this is me
right here
i'm not a little person in my head
right you say this is me i'm here i am
coming from my center so to me that
ground of being the sense of beingness
the sense of being here
again comes down to our bodies
comes down to our hearts comes down to a
reality that cannot be
described by the mind but we can at
least try our best to point
our way there
and
that sense of beingness spaciousness
depth
is
close to describe this reality that is
fundamentally indescribable
so so do you have i mean in your
retreats in your teaching yoga
meditation do you
is this often profound to people um
because i because for me um i didn't
grow up with it with a spiritual
background at all it was only you know a
few years back
where i started just going you know deep
on on youtube and in different apps and
reading different books and stuff and
i'd have these experiences where you
know i can kind of
feel my awareness you know quote unquote
drop drop into the heart and it it was
something i hadn't really
hadn't really i don't think i've felt
before
um
what's your experience when you're
teaching people is this ever kind of a a
light switch for people is it
what's the difference between a thinking
mind
yeah it is such an interesting question
um it's very tempting for me to be like
absolutely everyone in my
classes have a profound and
life-changing experience
i do remember one time leading a
three-week yoga teacher training and at
the end of it there was this student who
was getting her phd at a you know big
fancy university
and she said something along the lines
of i've learned more in this course that
was three weeks right than i have in my
entire
phd program
and
i was like
i
it's so true that you know in our
society we teach a lot of things we
teach chemistry we teach history we
teach physics
but rarely do we teach what is most
essential
and as you know in that book the little
prince what is most essential is of
course invisible to the eye
but
that was all just a preface to say that
i have found
as a teacher or facilitator i can't
teach anybody anything
especially if they're not wanting to
learn
like you know you could be like listen
to something and be like this is a bunch
of crap like i don't believe any of this
you can have all sorts of resistance you
probably know the story of the professor
and the team master and he's like teach
me zen and the team master
is pouring tea into the cup until it
overflows and
the professor is like hey what are you
doing he's like this is your mind your
cup is so full i can't put any more
knowledge into it you have to empty your
cup
and
so one of the things that we do discover
on the path is that we all have a source
of wisdom within all of us
right and this is very contrary to what
we did for the first 18 years of our
life we were
where we were told that in order to
learn something we have to take external
information and stuff into our brain
right we have to read this book we have
to go to the library you have to listen
to a professor who knows things and then
internalize that information and that is
one way of gaining certain understanding
of the world but something we discover
on
a spiritual path is that our inner space
is just as vast as outer space and that
there is a source of wisdom inside of us
that we can get in touch with
so i do think all i can do with anything
that i ever teach is just point
hey look what's inside of there what
happens when you do this
is there anything beyond the continuous
movement of thinking is there any part
of your experience that goes beyond
the general narrative that you have been
taught but it's up to the student to
uh to do it do it right so sometimes the
the dharma or the teachings or the path
is described as a door that is being
opened
but you as the student as the
practitioner have to walk through it
so you've also probably heard that basic
idea that when the student is ready the
teacher will come
and i
i
feel like people misinterpret this
lesson
because there's it almost seems like
magical thinking like once you're ready
poof this teacher will just appear right
in front of you
but it doesn't work that way it really
works that once you become fully ready
you will discover the myriad of teachers
both living and non-living both human
and non-human that
are all around you at all times you will
open yourself up and you can learn just
as much
from a flower
as you can from your breath
as you can from
shinrikyo suzuki or amma or somebody
else that some other guru teacher that
you enjoy
and it's that
that to me is the truth of it is that
once you're ready then
you are open to learning
so much from all the teachers that are
around you
yeah there's so there's just a wealth of
knowledge happening
maybe even knowledge isn't the right
word but a wealth of
wisdom perhaps happening at all times if
you could just tune tuned to it in a way
you know there's so much to be learned
there's so many
sometimes i like to
you know in a sense compare life to a
video game of all right what's what's
the world what's this level that i'm on
today trying to teach me you know
because if you're open to actually
learning like uh dang this thing
happened to me oh i locked my keys in my
car well dang you know it could you know
it switches you from that mindset of
this always happens to me or this is so
hard for me to handle into like what can
i learn from this you know um did you
absolutely
so i i really love um
um you know in in the poetic world
i like to think of
i think poetry is is one of one of the
closer things to koans you know it's
it's that ushering in of epiphany it's
that
um
that little
you know
the the you have the finger pointing at
the moon for sure um but so what's
what's your journey with poetry yourself
in your own writing like how did you
stumble upon this did you have any poems
when you first started writing you first
started reading that you're like oh that
is that does do that pointing to
something much more profound or did you
have any koan sort of experiences when
you first started with poetry
it's so lovely that you are bringing up
a koan because
this is something that i've found also
in my teaching
because we in the west we kind of have
this basic idea that a good teacher
is one who is able to sum up summarize
and explain really challenging difficult
concepts in a really simple way that we
can understand
right
but then you go to say like a zen
monastery and
a good teacher is one that makes things
so it possibly and intentionally
difficult
that in your struggle to wrap your head
around it you attain a new
and different level of understanding
and so you know the common trope is that
you go to your
zen master and you're like
why am i here what is the nature of
existence and he'll be like
how much does three pounds of grain
weigh
and you're like what
and then later you go how much does
three pounds of grain weigh and he'll be
like
the coral in the ocean reflects the
light of the moon
so too everything arises from the
emptiness that you are and like whatever
like if it's metaphysical they go
literal if it's literal they go
metaphysical and that to me is what a
colon is meant to do is it's meant to be
something the mind cannot grasp
and then as you struggle
to
find the
solution to the unsolvable problem that
occulon creates is
in that struggle eventually something
new gets kind of squeezed out of you
so i am a big fan of colons and i am a
big fan of poetry
which is also designed to
express a new way or a different way of
being
an understanding in the world
and
you mentioned
what poets or poems have expired have
inspired me early on and there's been
so many
but one i one quote i particularly love
is jane hirschfield and in one of her
books
she says that poetry
is both an amplification
and a clarification
of the human experience
i like that
and
you will find way more about what it
means to be human in
a poetry book than you will in the
dictionary
like the mind again wants those literal
definitions they want everything to they
wants everything to be laid out nicely
organized
and
um but the world doesn't doesn't work
that way
so
um
does that answer your question no yeah
it certainly does i mean i i love you
bearing with me zack too because a lot
of my questions are just kind of like
rambling thoughts and then i trail off
into a question mark so i i appreciate
you playing along um so you've already
written a couple poetry books you've
already written um you have your book
two the seven lessons of love heart
wisdom for troubling times
tell me a little bit about your book and
your two works of poetry and i also
understand you're working on another
book too which or another poetry book
too which i want to get to but tell me
about uh
what are kind of like the summaries of
of what you've written thus far
yeah well it's interesting because the
one that that's most prevalent i feel to
our current conversation is my most
recent book
it's gonna come out in june first i'm
not sure when this podcast will be aired
but it does tap a lot into many of the
things that we haven't got discussing
because my most recent book is called
pebbles which is designed to bring
imagery of just like a zen garden has
many pebbles that represent harmony and
with the nature and the universe
and
there's themes of zen and
interdependence and spiritual awakening
and nature and of course
what it does mean to live from the heart
and to have a conceptualization
of this world that goes beyond the mind
so earlier for example when we were
talking about the past
and the future and the mind
doing a really good job at making our
lives insufferable
because it's the mind that will want
things to be different right i know many
people love that phrase that pain is
inevitable but suffering is optional
and
i never quite resonated with it until i
came across a quote by saad guru the
great yogi
and he's just said that pain is physical
and suffering is
psychological which points to it's the
mind that wants things to be different
than what they are which to me is the
root of suffering suffering is simply
any time things are
not what we wish them to be
non-acceptance yeah all right so one of
the poems in pebbles i can read it to
you now
says
we either miss someone
or miss the missing
at home we long for the home that was
or will be
or never was
never content to just be
or sit with the flowers that only grow
in the shadows of others
you know a lot of the human experience
like is wanting things and then
getting it and realizing it's not what
we want
right we're like the doc
chasing after the car and then once we
finally get it we like don't know what
to do with ourselves
[Music]
because it's not that you want like the
ferrari or the mansion
or it's that you want the level of peace
security and safety that you think that
the material object object is going to
provide for you that's that's big that's
i think that's actually a a huge thing
that many people
you know i i was about to say wrap your
minds around it but i don't know if
that's appropriate um
that is that is very big you know we we
the feeling that comes with
the thing or the accomplishment that
we're striving towards or we think we
can obtain
that's what we're actually looking for
and um i think you'll agree that you
know a lot of it a lot of the spiritual
path is trying to find that here and now
without anything else without you know
how is how is everything that i have now
okay how how can i find peace with what
i have now
absolutely
there's that's one of the basic
teachings we have on the spiritual path
is that
nothing can bring you lasting happiness
um but you have it already
until you disturb it that's uh i believe
it's swami sachitananda who said that
and we tend to think that we tend to be
in the state of desiring
you know we want
we have this if only mind if only such
and such were to occur then i could be
happy if only i made more money if only
my boss wasn't such a jerk if only my
partner really understood me
and the mind
is plastic if we are constantly desiring
and wanting things to be different it's
going to
that's going to turn into a state that
the mind
continually comes back to
so sure enough you get the thing that
you want
and you're happy for a little bit but
you don't associate that happiness with
the fact that just for a brief moment in
time you've stopped desiring
anything
at all
right and you were present
yeah
yeah okay so what was your process with
uh with writing pebbles um is it do do
you have like a daily i wake up and i
write at this time or do you kind of
like let it influence you as it comes
about you know maybe you can catch a
thought and that starts your your poem
for me a lot of times i'm like i know i
want to write today i have some time
and you know a lot of times i feel like
as long as i'm open to it i can get at
least the first couple lines and then
it's you know a domino effect when i
write so what was your process like and
what kind of sparked you at the
beginning when you were writing pebbles
yeah i appreciate i love your questions
jacob here i really appreciate you
asking asking about my path and
um
and i'll tie it back into your asking
about some of my earlier works and my
first poetry collection was called
drinking roses on sunday which was my
poetic way of saying that love is my
religion
because roses to me
exemplified romance and love and sundays
when you normally go to church
so it's a lovely name by the way lovely
name i remember that
it's all just like literally just
bathing and drinking of love
as part of your religion
and
then i've always resonated with poetry
loved poetry would read tons of poetry
in my classes and lessons so i have like
you know a document of just hundreds of
poems that that i've gathered and found
over the world
in my in the world
and after a while i was like you know i
kind of want to write my own poems that
i read like during poses like shavasana
and yoga class so i started writing my
own poems and sharing those in class and
then those poems became
108 shavasana poems
which i beta tested myself in meditation
and yoga classes just reading it before
during or after shavasana
and you know we tend like with with any
creative field there's always less some
vulnerability of putting your work out
there and then having it be judged by
others you know you spend like five
years making a movie and then some
reviewer is like this is a steaming pile
of garbage you pretend like it doesn't
affect you but it kind of does but i
bring this up because there was one
amazon reviewer who with 108 shavasana
poems was like
these poems are too long
and i was like all right whoever you are
this pebbles is for you because okay all
right my intention with pebbles wasn't
wasn't
you know inspired by that review but my
intention with pebbles is just as a
pebble something beautiful and small
that you can hold in your hand
the intention was beautiful
elegant small
poems that just
brighten your day or just give you
another way to think about your day
so i i really came back to that quote i
want to say it's from the little prince
again that perfection is not when
nothing can be added but when nothing
can be taken away
so literally the whole time i was
writing i was like what words do not
need to be in this poem
this is a big word how can i turn it
into a smaller word how can i turn three
syllables into two how can i shave it
down to just capture the pure essence of
what this poem is trying to get across
so minimalism
elegance these were really huge
intentions when writing this there are
some poems that are like five words six
words seven words there's even a poem
that's two words
i love it cool but
um that's one of the beautiful things
about just poetry in general
is that everything that we do when we
write can become a tool and what i mean
by that is
like with a book
you write a paragraph and just to fit
the paragraph on the page you have to
take the line and put it on the next
line all right but with poetry anything
can be tool including where's the line
break like when are you going to hit
that enter space
right but you can also play with
punctuation you can also play with where
the word is on the page you can also
play with
paragraphs or what we call stanzas right
in between
so in this way like nothing is
unnecessary right if you see a comma or
a period or a question mark or a line
break it all is meant to
get some meaning across
[Music]
yeah yeah the the
the space in between is also you know
just as important as the as the the
words right
yeah wow wow that's really cool um so
it's as far as your your journey with
yoga
when you first started yoga versus where
you are now as a teacher and you've had
many years under your belt um
what's what's the difference in your
understanding you know and i ask that
because i like to you know if there's
anybody listening who
perhaps they don't really they haven't
really explored the world of yoga and
maybe they they just it's like oh well
it's just another workout i mean they're
going to go to the gym and hit the
weights or i'm going to do yoga
i like to kind of like expand um
[Music]
i guess yeah like what what is yoga to
you and how has it changed from when you
first started till now
if it has
yeah i mean it's a really excellent
question because absolutely when i
started up i kind of treated yoga the
way most people treat yoga nowadays is a
hour-long workout that you do
you know two three four times a week
and i really
got into yoga because of its physical
benefits because i had injured my back
and this was my path of healing
and at the beginning i do kind of think
that the way you know many of us
practice yoga is it's almost like
dipping our toe
into this vast and incredible
ocean of understanding
and i've been really getting into
just
south
indian south asian religions
spiritualities and philosophies
and one of the things i've discovered
you know you don't think about this but
you take a psychology class and they
almost pretend like psychology was
invented 100 years ago
by young or freud right and then you
take a history class in like the united
states is like 200
50 years old
and you don't realize what it's like or
i haven't didn't realize what it's like
to be in a country with 5 000 years of
history behind it
and
that our understanding of the mind of
ego of consciousness of did not begin a
hundred years ago but for three thousand
years there have been communities and
spiritual communities
that have
tapped into the nature of the mind
consciousness and come to incredible
psychological understandings of how the
mind works and how it creates suffering
and how to be free of it
this is it's funny because
i want to say like there's this
incredible infinite amount of knowledge
that yoga does tap you into you could
take any small slice of yoga and spend
the rest of your life studying it right
you could become a sanskrit scholar if
you want to get into that you could
become a scholar of southeast
asian philosophies you could also become
a physical therapist or something like
that right
so
but i say all of that because
that still does come from a mind and one
of gathering knowledge which is
distinctly different from simply
becoming wise and i would say i've done
tons of workshops
trainings
i got a master's degree in east west
psychology
and i'm constantly learning and by far
the greatest teacher i have found is
literally the breath
it's like
your own breath will teach you
everything that you need to know about
yourself about life about the nature of
reality
and so much more
and if i
were to sum up like the way i'm thinking
about yoga now which i think is really
important is
there's this word in sanskrit called
darshan or darshana
and
we in the west would translate that to
mean philosophical school which is to
say yoga is one of the 10 or 11
philosophical philosophical schools of
ancient india along with say buddhism
and mamansa and shankya and different
things like that
but when you get to this word it
literally means way of seeing
or worldview
and this is something i've just been
really trying to tap into is when we do
look out into the world what do we see
what do we interpret
and you can have a totally
different world view depending on what
you've been taught what you've been led
to believe by
the
system and culture that you've brought
up in
so just one example i often use is like
when you look out and you see a tree
what do you see
all right well first of all tree is a
label that comes from the mind
right but you might see an organism
undergoing photosynthesis from the sun
you might see a species right that's one
darshan that's one darshana
another way to see it is do you see the
manifestation of the tree spirit
right do you see mother earth offering
her gifts to the world
right do you see a home an ecosystem for
countless creatures
right or are you a buddhist do you see
emptiness there is fundamentally no
treeness
to this thing
right so
that's really the thing that's been
resonating with me most is thinking
about like what do you see when you look
out into the world is it a scientific
view it or is it something else
so how do you you know
a lot of times
i i find joy in you know
explaining or kind of like
conversing
science and spirituality you know
because i always it's it's often
one or the other like if you believe in
science then you don't believe in any of
that woo-woo stuff you know it seems
like it's like that all the time and
it's it's not exactly like that um so we
in in your studies with your masters i'm
sure you you probably came across things
that were you know i'm sure profound
profound to you um in your understanding
east and west psychology what are some
of the bigger differences that someone
might be able to like oh wow i never
thought about that before when it when
it comes to studying east versus west
understanding of psychology
yeah it's an excellent question and you
frame it really well when you talk about
this artificial bifurcation that we have
created between science and spirituality
which kind of happened like in the
western world for i want to say like
14th 15th 16th century
when science was coming to a different
understanding than the popular you know
christian belief at the time right we
were starting to discover that we're not
the center of the universe not even the
center of our own solar system oh no it
hurts to know it
and then there was this this split right
and
um
this is our
we have in the west because again we've
all been
raised to believe a certain certain
things about the world and we do have a
very particular darshan very particular
world view
very particular categorization system
that we have in our minds
around what science is
around what religion and spirituality is
and i'll also even throw the role of the
state in
um to say this is just one way of being
it's not necessarily good or bad but
there are pros and cons to each right
like we do have a separation between
church and state and many people think
it's this really incredible thing and
there obviously are huge benefits and
less tyranny from you know radical
radical believers
um
but
there are totally other ways to organize
one's entire entire um
society
around the sacred around the spiritual
right so you go to something like bali
with the island of bali in indonesia
which practices a very unique blend of
what they call a gamma hindu dharma very
interesting blend of buddhism so you'll
see you know buddha heads everywhere and
hinduism and you'll see ganesha's
everywhere and then their own kind of
indigenous belief systems
and like by law like every
every little town has to have a temple
in the middle of it
right and
when i
when i'm getting to that is um
part of our western darshan is we do
almost see religious life as what i call
like an extracurricular activity
like for most people like
every sunday you go to some church for
like two hours of your day
and that's like it like that is the
extent to which you are integrating
these belief systems and then you go to
work which is very you know secular to
the point of being completely sanitized
of any other way of being
and then you might have a scientific
endeavor which again is separate is very
separate from one's own religious or
spiritual understanding of the world
and as a result like we might put
we don't put yoga in the same
category as science
right but absolutely in india and the
east they would say this is absolutely a
mind-body
empirical
science
that has been developed over thousands
not just like a hundred years of
psychology over thousands of years
that shapes
uh everything that we do
in the world
that shapes uh what we do when we wake
up
it shapes our darshan how we view the
world shapes how we organize our society
organize our family structures
and
so like just one example is you know the
eightfold path of buddhism we have right
action and we have right livelihood
right so it's not just like you can work
for the oil company over here
and
destroy you know valuable ecosystems and
cause global warming and then come over
here and then meditate and call yourself
a good buddhist as long as you go to
church
right
there's right action you have to you
infuse it into into everything it is
that you do
so
um
you know to me yoga is all about that
linking together
you know some say the etymology of yoga
is simply one of linking or being
together experiencing unity and
recognizing that that artificial
separation of science and spirituality
or the sacred and the secular is again
the mind creating a world of separation
and part of our path is to bring it
bring it all back together
yeah okay i like that yeah okay so what
is um
[Music]
i mean i i i definitely want to answer
the the what is love question that's
always wonderful i'm sure you have a
great answer for that um
you know so let's go there let's go with
what is love
um and then
also how can we like extrapolate it out
from
it's such a
such a household term but it's um
it's something like so deep like it's
really is such an understanding like
everything really is all love and so
many like our entire reality is is love
in a sense so let's uh let's see what
you what you where you go with it zach
what is love
all right there's so many ways i could
go with it but i tend to just start
with one of the most simplest and
straightforward ideas
that all love is
is a genuine concern
for another person's well being
and this is largely informed by some
buddhist philosophy
and you might know what are known as the
four brahmaviharas or the four divine
abodes or the four noble qualities
where if you embody these qualities you
become a noble and good person
and
all of these qualities or three of the
four qualities are what happens when our
love touches another person what happens
when our genuine concern for another
person's well-being
touches that person and how they are
doing in their life
so one of the brahmava horrors is simply
compassion
which is what happens when our love
meets somebody who is suffering somebody
who is having a challenging experience
in their life
compassion is that desire for that
person to be alleviated of their
suffering
right
when our love touches somebody who isn't
suffering but they're doing pretty okay
turns into loving kindness
which is one of my most favorite
concepts you've probably heard the poly
word meta or the sanskrit mighty tree
and
i often like to just use the sanskrit
words because there's never a perfect
translation
so we don't even have a word for meadows
we had to combine two words
to combine loving and kindness
and then another phrase that another
concept that
is really helpful
is the third rama vihara which is mudita
which is sympathetic joy which is joy in
somebody else's joy
which is to say that if you
love somebody and you want them to do
good
or do well not to suffer and they're
doing pretty good then you have medita
you have sympathetic joy you are happy
that they are happy
all right which runs so contrary to like
the enemy and the jealousy that we tend
to experience when another person like
good things happen to another person
that you know isn't happening to you
like your coworker comes in and they're
like oh i just got that promotion i got
a big raise weren't you also wanting
that right not a whole lot of modita
not a whole lot of mudita there
but i love all of these things
i love compassion loving kindness and
sympathetic joy or join somebody else's
joy
and that concept of modita or
sympathetic joy is also really crucial
to love because there's a lovely
researcher
i think she was a
university of north carolina chapel hill
named
barbara frederiksen
and she has this book called love 2.0
and does
research again
scientific empirical research around
what love is and then she uses this
basic idea of positivity
resonance
and looks at how literally
physiologically you resonate with
somebody that you love with that you
love
and when you're guess what it's amazing
if you're happy if you want somebody to
be happy and they want you to be happy
you get happy guess what they get happy
that you're happy and then you're happy
that they're happy that you're happy and
then you just resonate in this happiness
resonance that just
that just takes you up it takes you up
to the sky
and that's one of the reasons just one
of why love is so powerful and
transformational because it has the
capacity to take us to places we never
would have dreamed of
all right so and this again when you
look at relationship science this tends
to be
more important
and more crucial towards successful and
happy relationships
and that by and large yes in a
relationship you want to be there for
your partner if they're having a hard
time you want to you want to
have some compassion for them
but what they have found when they look
at successful and happy couples is while
being there during the hard times is
important what's just as if not more
important
is rejoicing in each other's happiness
when your partner comes home and says
this great thing happened today the
successful happy couples are ones that
are like oh my gosh that's so amazing
yeah
yeah that's great okay so so what do you
in you you know you you're a love coach
so you you you teach love in a sense so
what does it look like at the beginning
you know when you you have people come
in and you're
i mean
i think it'd be kind of strange to sit
down like all right teach me about love
like i don't know you know everybody
thinks they probably have their own
version of love we think we understand
love
like is there
is there unlearning that that you feel
you you have to teach often in uh you
know when you're when you're
in your you know love coaching scenario
situation
so i got to qualify a few things because
first you're saying do i teach
and again you can't teach anything
okay
and you've also probably noticed how
free and glib
advice can be in this world
so also you know as coaches we don't
um
offer advice for example which can be
cheap and doesn't same advice doesn't
work for everyone
let me just back up a little bit because
i think most
people are familiar with life coaching
where you kind of have somebody and you
have your kind of you know you go
through your like eight part part chart
together and you work on your career and
you work on your family and you work on
your health and your wellness
and
what i have found
and i don't i don't have too much time
to explain it is it all ends up coming
back to
love and connection and belonging and if
we are to get to the root
the true root of our happiness and the
cause of our suffering it does come back
to love
and that
anything that
brings us on the path of happiness is
that brings us more on the path of love
and our suffering in life is that
of a result of lack of love
so indeed i love
coaching people into helping them
resource themselves
right
recognizing that everything that you
need is already within you
and all you have to do is
bring it out all we have to do is reduce
it all we have to do is recognize that
you're already strong
already capable
already know
what it is that you need to do and this
current
challenge that you are experiencing
so
people do experience challenging things
around love in a number of ways we can
easily divide it up between self other
and
well let me divide it up into
self love
love between individuals and love
between groups and communities right so
family for example would be in groups
and people struggle in all those
categories at different times in their
life so there are people that struggle
with self-love you know loving and
accepting themselves there are people
that are struggling in their friendships
they want deeper more authentic more
connecting friendships
there are people that struggle with
groups like their family believe it or
not i know it can be hard to believe but
some people don't have the most loving
supportive relationships with their
family
wow
[Laughter]
but also what's really crucial too is
just is this community
is we have really forgotten that uh
we've really evolved to grow up in a
network of supportive people that know
us and understand us
and all those things are of course kind
of connected to each other
so
everything from romantic relationships
to dating to long term to sex and
sexuality
there are lots of people out there who
are struggling with
having
an experience of love in their lives
with themselves with a romantic partner
with their community
and i helped them along
on that path
that's beautiful what what a great field
to be working in that's so great that
you do any of that
everything you do is awesome as far as i
would send zach um so so you have had a
podcast for a while now you're almost i
notice you're uh you're up right around
100 episodes so you have i don't know if
it's a new guest every single episode
but 100 episodes you've got to have
learned something
through that series by now is there
anything like a blanket statement like
what have you learned from podcasting
so you you're a good interviewer jacob
you've done your research this is
awesome i should i would if i was there
i would give you a hug or pet back or
something hug received virtually
virtual zuma
thanks zach
um it's true you know i
i used to run this workshop series
called learn to love where i'd bring in
a new speaker to speak in a new topic
and it was just a lovely community and a
lovely community event that we were to
have
and
covet up ended all of our lives
and everything shifted online so i was
like okay i can shift this online so i
did start a podcast around covet
happened
and i called it the learn to love
podcast
and i was like we'll see how long
this goes
you know how long we're isolated from
each other
and as you as we have all discovered
things have gone a lot longer than any
of us ever would have two weeks lasted a
little bit longer
but with every crisis there is
opportunity
and i have kept it going so every week i
interview a new guest it's either a
therapist or a coach or an educator or a
researcher
and i we have questions on love sex
intimacy and
relationships and i have really been
enjoying the entire experience
you know i've been learning about and
researching the nature of love for at
least 10 years now so i like to think
that i know a thing or two about a thing
or two
but
me myself i've learned so much
from all of my guests it's been really
incredible
and it's also been nice that we get to
connect with anybody wherever they may
be in the world we're no longer
geographically limited and we also get
to reach an audience that is
anywhere in the world
so
absolutely i've learned a lot about
communication the importance of
compassion
we've talked about sex love intimacy
monogamy non-monogamy long-term
relationships all that
and
you know there's
again there's all sorts of lessons that
i've learned
but
i do want to just go back to this basic
idea because i i do feel i still have to
convince people that love is the reason
that we are here on this planet because
there's always that resistance yes yeah
tell me because i'm telling you it's not
just some it's not just some far out
ideal
but
you know everyone that i've been talking
to
from psychologists at stanford
university
to a therapist in the deep south
to
um you know recovering
evangelical christians and
coaches and therapists
they all have expressed the same message
that we all need love from
the cradle to the grave
so to speak
we all need to be
seen
understood
recognized for who we are
and there is nothing more special
or essential
as
love
and just to give you like one example
when i talked about
love affecting our health
right
and what's interesting is
the presence of
love in one's life lowers the risk
factor one has for all
all of them all causes of death
right every last one from heart disease
to cancer
to suicide right you think that would be
like on the front page of every news
station
if you think but
well you probably saw again saw that
like there was this this longitudinal
study at harvard university i'm pretty
sure it was done by george vallant who
also wrote this amazing book spiritual
evolution and after 70 years they also
of you know harvard scientific long-term
longitudinal research they also came to
the same conclusion
right
and
and you're like how does that work right
what do you mean all causes right and
it's like
what i often point out it's very
interesting what evolution has wired us
to do and not to do
so for example i can easily take my arm
up i can move my arm down
what i cannot do is take my sadness up
and take my sadness down
we were wired to regulate our emotions
our stress
with
other people around us
what does help you bring your sadness
down bring your anger down
talking with somebody sharing it with
somebody being vulnerable with somebody
so
obviously love does help us regulate our
own nervous system which has a bounty of
health and positive health effects
but life is hard
and none of us can do it alone
so when we look at like well why is love
a risk factor for suicide well it's like
one way to say measure somebody's
um
subjective experience of of love and
connection you know you give them a
survey right so what are you going to
ask them so one thing you might ask them
is do you have anybody in your life that
you can share a secret with or
emotionally confident right you might
also ask them is there anybody in your
life that you could borrow 500 from
if you like really needed it right and
unfortunately with each subsequent
generation we're more lonely and
isolated than ever before so the numbers
are getting worse
but you know even a quarter of people
now have nobody nobody in their life
that they can talk to right
so what happens when you can't borrow
500 from somebody well
when you're behind on rent
guess what you get kicked out guess what
you're homeless guess what you can't get
mail you can't get a job right it easily
puts you on this downward spiral that
will end up with some
over overall bad effects you know
suicide alcoholism different things like
that
so
this is this is real this isn't again
some kind of sky ideal this is real
life
and this basic idea that we absolutely
need others
to be happy and to survive
yeah beautiful that's
yeah that's a it's something
in so many ways it seems so obvious you
know but but we forget you know we get
we get too caught up in the
to caught up in the details you know and
we forget the importance of just love so
um one one thing that did pop into my
mind um something that i
you know i think is something that i
still that i still am trying to unwind
in many ways in my own psychology is
transactional love like you do this for
me i'll do this for you um i like it it
was it was something that i i think that
i learned at a young age as like a
survival technique sort of thing
um and i think it took me a while to
kind of
unfold it and um you know you know trust
the people when they're like dude if you
need anything call me like you know to
really trust them like well i you know
what if
what if i don't answer my phone when you
called though and i missed my miss the
phone call and you know i don't know
it's um
does anything spark to mind from that
when i say transactional love and
unwinding that belief
uh yes the fundamental
inquiry
around
unconditional love
if it's possible
if it's worth it can it be done
you know you might read something like
osho you probably know
and he has this dialogue and he says
something along the lines of
you know what most people call love is
not love it's just a transaction it's
just i will love you if you do these
things for me
you know if you tell me i'm beautiful
and you meet my emotional needs and you
do these things for me then i will love
you if you cease to do these things
my love will be quite conditional
you know if you
i'll just like
cheat on me if you do some some terrible
transgression my love will very quickly
turn to hate
and um it is it is
kind of incredible you know there's a
certain the relationship that people do
have with their exes right the things
that you sometimes hear people say and i
don't want to diminish like the very
real emotional pain and trauma that one
can experience in a romantic and loving
relationship but just merely to observe
that somehow we have gone from you're
the most important person in my life i
love you with every fiber and cell in my
being
to
i mean
now you're just somebody i used to know
two
here's my restraining order
[Laughter]
yeah so
um
the question you know so the question
kind of begins um what
what are we to do about this and is
is that love is it real love and what
does unconditional love look like
and i've
personally
again there's many different ways i
could kind of approach it from
but
one thing i often find that people
forget
on the path towards unconditional love
is the most important person
you
is
you can love everyone
okay this is the path our path is to
love everyone without conditions believe
it or not
and who else
you you are included in that everyone
because that to me it tends to be one of
the biggest obstacles
um because you do find i say like oh you
should love everyone open your heart as
much as you can and people will say
oh so someone in an abusive partnership
should just stay there because you know
they love their partner or they're
staying together because they love their
kids it's like hold on i think you
forgot somebody
you also need to love yourself you also
need to have a genuine concern and love
for your own being
so
there's absolutely more like tender
versions of love like i've been had a
really rough day i'm gonna have a bubble
bath take care of myself
and they're also more young more fierce
versions of love such as
in order for me to love myself i need to
set up this boundary i need to
um
protect myself in a certain way
right so
no absolutely not don't stay in an
abusive relationship because
of the love you have for your partner or
your kids because once you have a really
healthy and supportive love for oneself
which again has to be unconditional are
you gonna
stop loving yourself because you made a
mistake
no you have to recognize we all make
mistakes we're all human we're all as
ramdas would say walking each other home
we're all
uh our actions are unfolding according
to our own karma and conditioning
and
you can so when you do have this that
healthy self-love an important part of
that is appropriate boundaries
is being like i respect myself and honor
myself and i expect the people in my
life to respect me honor me take care of
me if you cross this boundary part of my
self-love practice will be to
separate and believe it or not i know
this might be tough for you know some
folks to hear
but
you can
absolutely
love somebody
and
i'll say push it's kind of an active
word but i'll say and push them out of
your life
or make the appropriate separation that
you need between you and them so that
they are not causing you unnecessary
suffering and you can say listen i love
you
you're an incredible human being
there's a fundamental goodness in all
people including in you
and
no longer can you be in my life
for these reasons
right yeah
so
opening one's heart to other people
doesn't mean you're gonna be some rug
that gets walked over
it doesn't mean that you have to
tolerate negative
behavior toxic relationships abusive
relationships
and that does start with
in my mind a
love for oneself
and part of that love recognizes that
you are imperfect and still worthy of
love you make mistakes and still worthy
of love
and we can extend that also to other
people
but we can also decide what people we
want in our life and what people we
do not want in our life right
so
even ram dot like ram das
the late ramdas you probably know
richard alpert who turned into ram das
like he used to stay like on his
altar
he would have a picture of you know
jesus
and buddha and then
dick cheney dick cheney
[Music]
and you look at like how can you know
what is stopping me from loving this
person right and
then that's that is part of the path is
looking at their own resistance to
loving another human being
yeah yeah i love that i find um a lot of
times in my meta or you know love loving
kindness meditations the thing that
really clicked for me the thing that
really worked for me um i use uh sam
harris's waking up app is is one i like
to use a lot but
the act of you know visualizing someone
that you know you know your dick cheney
or whoever it is visualizing that person
you know as a child you know they were a
child once and uh you know they had a
whole life but before they were who they
were and you know they had parents and
it kind of helps it's this little
doorway in you know and as a little tip
and trick for anybody if if it's
difficult often with meta um it's
difficult to immediately like think of
yourself and bring self-love to yourself
so um sometimes you could use that as a
little doorway you know if you're
imagining someone else as a child well
can you think of times when you were a
child like wouldn't you wish yourself
love too and if you could visualize you
know yourself as a seven-year-old or
something and
okay i can feel love for them it starts
to open a little bit of that heart heart
doorway in a sense you know into
yourself
absolutely i mean i sometimes repeat
this quote and i think people have heard
it so much it's almost turned into a bit
of a cliche but i'll just say it that as
rumi would put it your task is not to
seek for love but merely to remove all
the obstacles against it
and part of our path of moving from
conditions to unconditional love is
recognizing the own obstacles our own
obstacles that we have put in the way of
our love
and a huge part of that is looking at
the people
in our lives that we are
not loving and looking deeply at those
obstacles and i absolutely resonate very
much with that meditation we where you
progressively go to more challenging
people right
because that's that challenge is those
that challenge you the most that will
that are pointing out um
exactly where it is you need to grow the
most
yeah
yeah wow beautiful okay man well we're
getting up here in time um this has been
amazing like a whole episode about love
i couldn't ask for anything better it's
so great um so time has flown my friend
yeah it definitely has
we had a great conversation zach um i i
do want to make sure everybody knows you
know where to find you um you have an
instagram you're active on instagram you
post your new podcasts on there they
learn to love podcasts um they can they
can find can they find all of your past
writings on amazon or is
yeah all my books are available on
amazon for sure okay and then when when
is when does pebbles come out
june 1st
june reorder it now yeah cool yeah um
again i'm not i'm i'm strange when it
comes to posting episodes so i'm not
sure exactly when this is going to when
this is going to post
right now
yeah it could be um
i would love to if you're willing zach i
would love to um again if i didn't
mention anything that you want to make
sure everybody knows mention that but i
would love to go out on another poem if
you have another one you'd like to share
sure
um
so there's three sections of pebbles for
a second's pebbles second one is leaves
which has slightly longer ones longer
poems kind of designed to look like
leaves and the third one is petals
designed like a beautiful blossoming
flower
and
i bring this up because i don't want to
make it seem like love is just sunshine
and rainbows
or even that i'm just living in a state
of blissful sunshine rainbowy love
um
and i have found
that often on the path that
a broken heart is a gateway to an open
heart
and
definitely
it seems like right now
is a
time frame that breaks our heart more
and more
uh maybe
you know 10 years ago he would say the
same thing but there's so much going on
in the world from
i don't want to politically ostracize
anybody but i'll just say from abortion
rights to
ukraine to
a dying
world that is under threat right now and
that was another huge uh motivation for
pebbles is to cultivate a love for the
natural world
for mother earth madrithira pachamama
mother gaia
because in our expanding our love to
more and more people
we of course cannot forget the non-human
non-living uh not living but uh
non-human creatures
and that is our task to me is to keep
our heart open
uh throughout it all
to have the courage to
face
whatever it is that needs to be faced
right now the most pressing
issues
um
and who knows maybe by the time this
airs another
resting issue will be the main main
event hopefully not hopefully we can
keep the camera angles not at the new
new thing yeah
but part of our path to me has always
been to widen the circles of our
compassion
to more peoples and of course to the
natural world
so this is one of the poems that's in
petals so
he stands as just one petal on a big
flower
and it goes like this
they say the center of god's sphere is
everywhere
and the circumference nowhere
i have found the same to be true of an
open heart
it feels all things
those choosing wallpaper and those
wondering if they will make it to the
end of the day
the hawk missing its babies
and each blade of grass being cut
no stacking of selfish justifications
will ever take you near enough to the
sky
to taste its light where we live
drunk on cherry trees
dreaming of their bloom
that's lovely man that's lovely
well man thank you for sharing thank you
for sharing your poems um i'm looking
forward to checking out pebbles when it
comes out
um
thanks again for your time thanks again
for for sharing and uh of course you
know answering my my rambling questions
i appreciate it thanks for hanging with
me
thank you so much jacob i love your
open-ended questions and your
thoughtfulness just really cares through
in this work that you're doing so it's
been really wonderful to connect with
you
yeah absolutely likewise zach well
thanks so much um
listeners love yourself take care of
yourself you know breathe through your
nose breathe slowly
check out uh check out a yoga class and
see what you can learn from it besides
just the physical things so
yeah all right man we'll uh we'll be in
touch zach i will shoot you an email
when this does post and otherwise have
good rest your day buddy thank you jacob
namaste namaste
at what age do we learn how to have
better conversations
[Music]
at what age do we learn to have better
conversations with ourselves
[Music]
knowledge is power